#大家好 今天王剛兄弟過來我們家
Hi everyone! Today our brother Wang Gang came to visit us.
#我們帶他去抓我們山上的魚
We'll take him to catch some fish on the hill.
#順便把兄第他們都叫上
I've also asked other brothers to come with us.
#山上的魚 對 我們這山上有口池塘
Fish on hill?
Yes, we've a pond up there.
#我們放了好多魚
We've put a lot of fish there.
#哦 是你自己家的 我自己家的
I see. It's your pond.
Yea! It's mine.
#今天那麼多人不敢去禍害兄弟家哦
I am not going to loot my brothers when so many people are around.
#一個個禍害 不好 走啦
No, it's no good. Let's go!
#那我拿這個網魚的是嗎
This is for netting fish, right?
#呃 這個是網魚
Yes, it is,
#這個網魚
for netting fish.
#那這個鋤頭拿來是挖魚的嗎
And the hoe is for digging up the fish, isn't it?
#呃 鋤頭是 呃
Eh, the hoe is for, eh
#放水的
draining the pond.
#放水
Draining
#走啦
Let's go!
#這口池塘是我們自己家的哦 上次放了好多魚進去
This pond belongs to us. Last time I have put a lot of fish here,
#特別是蛇頭魚
especially snakehead fish.
#蛇頭魚放了最少有 二三十斤
I have put at least 10kg of snakehead fish.
#看一下 看能不能抓得到一桶
Let's see, let's see if we can catch, catch a barrel of them.
#哇 那裡好像有魚
Wa! It seems there are fish!
#誒 那不是
Ey? It's not a fish.
#是蜘蛛
It's a spider.
#看不到 我把這水放乾了就可以抓得到它啦
Can't see any. We can catch after after draining up the water.
#把這個褲腳搞起來一點
Let me roll up the jeans.
#草
Grass...
#割一下
Cut it!
#這個是山泉水來的哦
This is spring water.
#這牛皮袋都是我自己放下去的
This bag was dropped down by me.
#啊
Yoooh!
#跟我我那的井水差不多
It's quite similar to our well water.
#是啊
Indeed.
#你看 看到有魚了現在 看到了 看到了
See? You can see the fish now.
Yea, yea, I can see them.
#全部都在鑽哦 對呀
They are drilling into the mud.
Yep!
#就是不知道甚麼魚
But I don't know what kind of fish they are.
#你看
See?
#應該很多魚哦 這裡哦
There should be a lot of fish, here.
#老是在
The bubbles keep
#冒泡了
coming up.
#它冒泡是甚麼 是魚在下面
What do the bubbles mean? Does it mean that the fish are...
#鑽是吧 鑽 它是魚在下面鑽
drilling? Drilling, It's because the fish are drilling under the water.
#嗯
Um...
#它一動它就會冒泡
The movements make the bubbles.
#把你家的那個魚撈光了
We are going to catch all your fish.
#沒問題吧 沒事
Is that Okay?
No problem!
#兄弟家還有
My brothers still have a lot.
#哦
Oh...
#兄弟家就是我家的
My brothers' means mine.
#你家的還是我家的
And yours means mine.
#是啊 現在我們放的就是
It does. The pond that we are now draining
#就是我們自家的
is indeed ours.
#這個放水要一個多小時啊
The draining is going take more than an hour.
#等一下我帶你去廣東吃飯
Let's go to Guangdong to have a lunch
#廣東 對 哦
Guangdong?
Yes.
Oh..?
#就是 我們跟廣東交界 兩隔壁
You know, we are neighbouring Guangdong, at the border.
#好 我們
I see!
We can...
#翻座山過去就是了
get there after passing a hill.
#很近吧 很近的
Very close?
Yes, very close.
#啊 那還好 走路也可以過去
Ah, that's not too bad.
You are even walk there.
#我還以為
I thought we were
#坐個車去廣東吃個飯
driving all the way to another province just to have a lunch.
#不用不用不用 很近的
No no no! It's not that far.
#交界上
We are on the border.
#好 好
Good!
#我們準備走啦 我們等一下在[SIC]回來咯
Let's get ready!
Let's come back later.
#走 好
Alright!
Let's go!
#等一下再回來
Let's come back later.
#慢點
Be careful!
#沒事啊 我習慣了
No worries! I've get used to it.
#吃飯後
After lunch
#誒 這魚怎麼抓
Eh? How can I catch this fish?
#它在泥裡面
It's inside the mud.
#在淤泥裡面的
Yes, inside the mud.
#我要開個張
I'll catch at least one.
#這魚
The fish...
#這摸魚有點難度哦
It's a bit difficult to catch my hands.
#有點難度
A bit difficult.
#這裡
Here!
#你用丟過來啊
You need to throw it here.
#看著啊
It's coming!
#你在那邊你丟給她
You throw it to her on your side.
#丟給我
Throw it to me.
#哈哈哈哈哈
Ha ha ha ha ha!
#你丟得真好
What a gorgeous throw!
#還要大力點
You need to pour harder.
#大力點
Harder!
#這個
What the...!
#你不要挖那麼猛嘛
Don't be too ambitious!
#你半桶半桶的來
Get half a barrel at a time!
#舀這個水 很累的啊
Pouring the water....is very tiring
#那個腰累
on the lower back.
#還有那麼多水 差不多啦
That's the water remains. We're almost done.
#再搞兩下就沒啦
A few more times will be enough.
#把它削過來
Put it to this side.
#好 就放那裡
Alright! Put it right here.
#過來了嗎
Are you coming now?
#這條跑不了啦
This fish can't escape.
#你看 一條蛇頭魚 (註︰視頻中不知說甚麼，但字幕是蛇頭魚)
See? A snakehead fish!
#又是條鯰魚 是不
It's catfish again, isn't it?
#不是鯰魚 是那種
No, it isn't. It's like eh...
#蛇頭魚
Snakehead fish
#哦 這裡有一條
Oy! Here is one.
#你看 這條蛇頭魚
See? This snakehead fish.
#很漂亮的哦 這個蛇頭魚
It's pretty, the snakehead fish.
#不是很大 應該一兩 一兩就有
It's not too big. It should be fifty, just fifty grams.
#哇 這有一條
Wa! Here is one!
#哇 那麼長
Wa! It's so long!
#你看 這一條
See? This fish.
#那麼大條
It's so big!
#啊 這你跑得掉
You think you can run away?
#一些小鯉魚
There are small "li yu".
#你看 今天的收獲不錯吧
See? Not bad, right?
#那麼多條
We have so many fish.
#五六斤
Almost 3kg
#五六斤哦
Yeah, almost 3kg.
#下次能不能不要捉魚啦
Can we do some other things next time?
#搞甚麼
So what do you want?
#幹點輕鬆的好不好 這個好累啊
Something easier. Catching fish is too exhausting.
#誒 可以喲
Eh? Why not?
#放了半天水呀 我現在
I've been doing that all day long and I'm now...
#剛好兄弟家的板栗熟啦
The chestnuts at my brother's place is ready just now.
#我們下次去打板栗
We can knock down some next time.
#很好哇
Very good!
#打這個板栗
Knock the, the chestnusts.
#這個小的要不放掉一點吧
Do we need to release some small ones?
#好的
The small ones.
#好的不好做
It's not easy to cook the small ones.
#小的把它放了吧
So let's release the small ones.
#給你留點種好不好
Shall we leave some here?
#這些就放掉哦
These can be released.
#對
Right.
#這種太小啦
It is far too small!
#太小啦 把它放回去
It's too small. Put it back.
#放回去
Put it back.
#放生 這個鯉魚也放生
Release it, and this "li yu" too.
#這個鯉魚
This "li yu".
#放了 放了
Release it. Release it.
#這條大鯉魚也放掉
And this big "li yu" too.
#這個也放掉呀
This one too?
放掉
Yea!
#這種不好吃啊 還不夠大
It tastes nothing. It's still not big enough.
#啊
Ah?
#它能長很大的
It can get very big.
#好吃
No! It's tasty!
It's tasty!
#不放啦 不放啦 不放啦 不放啦
Don't put it back! No! No! No! No!
#太小啦 這個 還可以再長更大
It's too small. It can be even bigger.
#那這個呢
Then how about this one?
#這個
This one?
#嗯
Yea!
#這個不放吧
You aren't releasing it, are you?
#這個也放了吧 放個
I am. This one....
#放了呀
Again?
#不放啦 你留一條來吃嘛
No! Leave one for our meal!
哈哈哈
Ha ha ha
#那就這樣子哦
So that's what we have.
#這個
This is...
#蛇頭魚也放掉去
Release the snakehead fish too.
#不要 蛇頭魚
We don't want them.
#哇 這個 就這個
Wa! This one! Just this one!
#竄得最快的這個 這種
It's sweeping the fastest.
#算你運氣好
You are lucky.
#這條鯉魚也放掉
Release this "li yue" too.
#都沒魚啦
We have no more fish.
#是啊 都沒魚了呀
Exactly! Nothing is left.
#沒魚啦
No more fish!
#有
We do have fish.
#你都放完啦
But you released them all!
#你看 這樣的魚還可以長
See? These fish can still grow.
#這不放
No!
#哇
Wa!
#全部放啦
You released them all!
#還有
Not all.
We still have some.
#我帶你去河邊洗一下 你看 一身都髒不拉稀的
Come with me to the riverside to have a wash? See? You are all covered with mud.
#你確定只是洗一下而已哦
Are you sure that it's just a wash?
#洗一下
Have a wash!
#那麼髒 不洗乾淨來
So dirty! We must have a wash.
#走吧 走吧
Let's go! Let's go!
#你看 這個魚太小啦 這不好吃
See? The fish is too small. They won't taste good.
#把它放到我們池塘裡面去
Let me put it into my own pond.
#不對呀
Isn't something wrong?
#這不是弄來吃的嗎
Aren't we going to eat them?
#這太小啦 不好吃
They are too small. They won't taste good.
#這不小了
No, it's not small.
#哪裡
It is.
#這鰂魚剛剛好
This "ji yue" is just right.
#它還可以長很大的 這個鰂魚
This kind of fish can get very big.
#那我們今天不是白幹啊
So what's the purpose of all our effort today?
#沒事呀 兄弟家有板栗 我帶你去摘
No worries. My brother has chestnuts. You can pick some with me.
#板栗
Chestnues.
#很多的哦 板栗喲
He has a lot! Chestnuts!
#你確定
Are you sure?
#確定 真的
Yes, trust me!
#不騙你的
I won't fake you.
#白幹了一天活啦
Our effort is all in vain.
#哈哈哈
Ha ha ha
#沒事 等一下板栗很多
No. We'll get a lot of chestnuts.